<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Dr. Tancred Robinson, in answer to some passages in his to Mr. VVotton, relating to Mr. Harris's remarks on some late papers, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Harris, John, 1667?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.19.[25]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 777.l.1.[49]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224293</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">195781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 195781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; D2:1[28], E7:1[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Dr. Tancred Robinson, in answer to some passages in his to Mr. VVotton, relating to Mr. Harris's remarks on some late papers, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Harris, John, 1667?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.H.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>In reply to a letter, by Dr. Tancred Robinson, to Mr. William Wotton, B.D. Chaplain to ... the Earl of Nottingham ... some late remarks, &amp;c. Written by John Harris, A.M.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Robinson, Tancred, --  Sir, d. 1748 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wotton, William, 1666-1727 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious disputations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:195781:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:195781:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter to Dr. <hi>Tancred Robinſon,</hi> in Anſwer to ſome Paſſages in His to Mr. <hi>VVotton,</hi> relating to Mr. <hi>Harris</hi>'s Remarks on ſome Late Papers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU are pleaſed to ſay <hi>you have had very ill Treatment from me,</hi> tho <hi>you believe, I never ſaw you, nor ever received any Affront or Injury by your means.</hi> 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that (to my knowledge) I never did ſee you; as alſo that I know of no <hi>Affront</hi> or <hi>Injury</hi> you ever did or occaſioned me. And I do here aſſure you, that it was no <hi>Private diſguſt</hi> at Dr. <hi>T.R.</hi> that induced me to write the Diſcourſe that ſo much offends you, but a Reſolution to beſtow ſome Remarks on thoſe who from <hi>ſuch poor Piques</hi> will ſet themſelves by ſecret and unfair ways to oppoſe Truth, Undermine Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and True Philoſophy, and Blaſt the Reputation of thoſe that endeavour to propagate them. But wherein I have ill Treated you, I ſhall particularly enquire. And firſt, you charge me with <hi>Inſinuating that you are the Beaſt L. P.</hi> and that therefore <hi>I have fallen hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily on the Introduction to Sir</hi> John Narborough, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which I anſwer, that I no where call <hi>L. P. Beaſt,</hi> nor directly charge the Eſſays on you. 'Tis true, I hint now and then that there are ſome paſſages in them very like your way of writing; and by what <hi>you uſed to talk about Town</hi> before the publication of them, as well as what you are now pleaſed to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, 'tis plain without going any further, there is ground enough for an Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that nature. The Reaſon why I cited ſome things out of your Writings, was both becauſe (as I ſaid juſt now) I found a ſtrange agreement <hi>in Senſe</hi> and <hi>Stile</hi> between them and thoſe of <hi>L. P.</hi> and alſo that I found ſeveral <hi>paſſages there lyable to juſt Exception:</hi> and why I may not make Remarks on <hi>ſuch,</hi> wherever I find them, you have not yet convinced me.</p>
            <p>You <hi>ſolemnly declare you are not the Author of the two Eſſays;</hi> And yet you own that you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted towards the Compoſition of that Elaborate Pamphlet, being induced to it, not by any motives of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but (ſuch is your <hi>ſoft, gentle and Chriſtian meekneſs</hi>) by a <hi>Private diſguſt at D.</hi> W. But ſince you ſay you are ſorry <hi>that you were tempted to caſt your Eyes on ſome vicious Fragments of thoſe Patch'd Eſſays,</hi> and alſo that the Author hath made <hi>ſuch an ill uſe of your</hi> kind <hi>furniſhing him with Books and Letters:</hi> I declare <hi>I am ſorry</hi> too, that you did not prohibit the Publication of thoſe <hi>Patch'd Eſſays,</hi> and which had not <hi>you,</hi> as you ſay, <hi>toucht here and there,</hi> I had never <hi>toucht</hi> you. You muſt therefore Sir, thank your ſelf <hi>for the unkind Animadverſions you</hi> complain of; which how <hi>unkind</hi> ſoever they may appear to you, I am ſure are not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay indeed, that <hi>I have a peculiar faculty of bringing forth Monſters, catching here and there a line, and ſometimes ſingle words, piecing them together into one ridiculous Paragraph.</hi> Had you proved this, Sir, t'would lye as hard on me, as now it doth on you; but the Inſtance you give is very ſhort of it. You ſay, <hi>I introduce on my Stage the Monkeys and Apes (as before I had done Falſe Dice and Trick Tack) which if any one thinks it worth his labour to compare with your Letter to Mr.</hi> Ray, <hi>he will ſoon diſcover the Venom and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer of this Mercurial Remarker.</hi> But, Sir, your <hi>Invention</hi> it ſeems is much better than your Eye-ſight, for I make no mention of <hi>Falſe Dice</hi> any where, and not of <hi>Tick Tack</hi> till 76 pages after this: And for the <hi>Monkeys and Apes,</hi> 'twas your ſelf <hi>introduced them on the Engliſh Stage;</hi> as will plainly appear if the Reader pleaſe to peruſe that Letter of yours. In the Place you referr to, <hi>viz. p.</hi> 51. of my Remarks, I urge againſt <hi>L.</hi> P. that though it could be proved that the Foſſil Shells were not depoſited, where they are found, by the Deluge, yet would it not thence follow, that they were not Shells at all: And for this I bring the Teſtimony of the moſt Learned Doctor <hi>T. R.</hi> who tho he thought <hi>ſome of theſe Bodies might be ſcatter'd up and down the Earth by Encampments of Armies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or by Apes and Monkeys:</hi> yet calls them Shells notwithſtanding. Now in this, Sir, I do you no wrong, for the Paſſage in your Letter to Mr. <hi>Ray</hi> is only a little longer, but to the very ſame ſenſe. Say you there <hi>Mr.</hi> Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, <hi>the late French Envoy to</hi> Siam, <hi>affirms that the Monkeys and Apes are almoſt continually car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Shells, and other Marine Bodies from the Sea-ſide up to the Mountains.</hi> All I can be culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for here, is only that I did not cite the Authority from whence you had this Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that I call <hi>that your Opinion,</hi> which you had from Mr. <hi>Loubere.</hi> And is it not ſo? don't you bring this as one way, by which Shells may come to the Tops of Hills? Mr. <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere</hi> perhaps was ſo happy as to ſee the Monkeys and Apes about this important work; his
<pb facs="tcp:195781:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore was <hi>knowledge,</hi> and yours that relate it from him in that Letter, is <hi>Opinion</hi> of the Truth of that Fact: which is all I ſay of it. And therefore, wherein the <hi>Barbarity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer and Venom of this matter</hi> lies, you would have done better to have demonſtrated, than to have charged it <hi>unjuſtly</hi> and <hi>unfairly</hi> upon me, without doing ſo.</p>
            <p>Next, Sir, you charge me with <hi>Jirking</hi> at the <hi>Boyling and Burning Fountains,</hi> which you are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>are not ſo much as warm, and even actually cold</hi> (vid. <hi>My Remarks</hi> p. 59.) And really, Sir, I can't but think ſtill, that you deſerve a little Animadverſion for that manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing your ſelf. For if by <hi>Boyling</hi> and <hi>Burning,</hi> you mean as other People do, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true ſignification of thoſe words, you will find very few Perſons that will believe the Fact you Relate, <hi>viz. that Boyling and Burning Fountains are actually cold.</hi> But if by <hi>Boyling</hi> you mean nothing <hi>but a Fountain's bubbling</hi> up, I can't ſee what need there is of a Pompous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſuch a Fountain: For wherever there is a great Preſſure or weight of Water, and the Orifice of the Spring but Narrow: Or wherever any Air or Vapour comes out along with the Water, there this mighty Phaenomenon of the <hi>Bubbling</hi> or <hi>Boyling</hi> of the Water will follow: And yet it will be no great news to tell the World that you have ſeen a Spring bubble up, whoſe Water is cold. And then as to <hi>Burning;</hi> if by it you mean <hi>no burning of the Water at all,</hi> but only, an irruption of ſome Sulphurous or Bituminous Vapours at, or near the Fountain Head (which was the Caſe of the <hi>Spring</hi> near <hi>Wigan</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire, Phil. Tranſ. N.</hi> 26.) I think ſtill you had as good not have <hi>called it a Burning Fountain:</hi> And 'tis your <hi>pretty wording of</hi> it only, that I find fault withall; being ſatisfied there is in nature in many Places, ſomething like what <hi>you mean,</hi> without deſiring any <hi>old Woman to pour thoſe Fountains into my Skull,</hi> which (by a way peculiar to you) you ſay ſhe can ſo eaſily do.</p>
            <p>After this you tell Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> that I have ſome where or other, tho where you know not, <hi>a very nauſeous piece of Scurrility on himſelf for his Laborious and Accurate Account of Agoſtino Scilla:</hi> Now Sir, ſince you diſcourage Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> from Reading my Book, by a witty Argument drawn from its price, you ought to have been ſo juſt and kind as to have quoted that <hi>Nauſeous</hi> and <hi>Scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> Paſſage: But the miſchief is, there is no ſuch thing there. I never mention Mr. <hi>Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> once in all my Book, nor do I charge the <hi>Extract of Scilla</hi> on him: Indeed I ſay, <hi>that Extract is liable to Exceptions, and that I can prove it,</hi> and I ſay now that the Extracter ſhall have that Proof whenever he deſires it. But where is the <hi>Nauſeouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Scurrility</hi> of this: Alaſs, 'tis only a poor diſ-ingenuous Artifice of yours to prejudice Mr. <hi>Wotton</hi> and draw him into your Quarrel; and you practice the very ſame with reference to Dr. <hi>Hook,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Liſter:</hi> which I doubt not, but thoſe Gentlemen are well aware of: And now Sir, having finiſhed my Anſwer to the great Charge againſt me; pray give me leave to ask you a few Queſtions, and ſo I will leave you.</p>
            <p>And firſt Sir, I wou'd fain know whether your calling ſuch pretty Gentile Names as you do, ſuch as, <hi>Buffoon, Mountebank, Scaramouch, and Harlequin, Draw-Can-Sir, Leviathan, Fitz-Harris, Pueril Declamator,</hi> &amp;c. be ſuitable to <hi>that Chriſtian Meekneſs, and to thoſe ſoft and gentle Inſtructions you have ſo often been</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>inſpired withall?</hi> and whether it be agreeable to the kind promiſe you made of <hi>not treating me after my own Petulant and Inhumane Manner?</hi> and whether this be not a little ſuſpicious and moſt <hi>diſagreeable to the refined part of Mankind?</hi> to give it in your own way. 2dly. May not a man that ſo ſoon forgets his promiſed way of handling Mr. <hi>Harris,</hi> forget alſo whether he ever <hi>knew the Author of the two Letters</hi> or not? for indeed Sir, there are in them (as I obſerve in my Remarks) ſo many things agreeable to the Stile and manner of writing uſed by <hi>L. P.</hi> that they wou'd tempt any one to think they had the ſame Original. And truly Sir, there are even in this very Letter of yours a great many Touches which are very like the Maſterly hand of <hi>L. P.</hi> ſuch as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enom of this mercurial Remarker: ducking in a mighty Volum of vanity: Every old Womans being able to pour the Boyling and Burning Fountains into my skull:</hi> And that concluding piece of Elegance, <hi>that you are not affected with the Grimaces of Buffoons, and Mountebanks, unleſs by way of Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as in this</hi> J. H. <hi>his Remarkable Theatre of Scaramouch, and Harlequin: Judge you now of this Hue-in-cry from your Brother of</hi> Winchelſey: All which I think are enough to juſtifie a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark I have made at the top of my 51 Page: Which I will not here repeat, but leave you to conſider of it at your Leiſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am, SIR, Your humble Servant.</hi> J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:195781:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
